hello I'm your host David Bernard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
iding Our Guest today is Phil Carter an
independent growth adviser and angel
investor focused on helping consumer
subscription companies scale Phil spent
the last decade as a VC and product
leader at companies like Fair Quizlet
and iata on the podcast we talked with
Phil about how to effectively use
benchmarks to Aid decision- making the
limitations of benchmarks and why even
the best companies aren't top quartile
in every single metric hey Phil thanks
so much for joining us on the podcast
today yeah thanks for having me always a
pleasure Phil's back oh wait sorry I
interrupted David do my intro Jacob
always nice to chat with you as well I
still can't follow directions but but
I'm here so I'm I'm excited let's go so
Phil we are going to talk today about
your subscription value Loop calculator
and the reason I wanted to do this
episode and wanted to get this episode
out now is that me and my colleagues are
hard at work on the 2025 state of
subscription apps report and we're going
to share a ton of benchmarks and I think
people always are a little I wouldn't
say confused but we get a lot of
questions like what does this actually
mean what do we do and I think what
we're going to talk about today is going
to set the context for listeners of the
podcast anyway I hope everybody whoever
downloads the reports goes back and
listens to this but it's going to set
the context what do you do with
benchmarks like how do you actually make
good decisions from all of this St data
and so I love the calculator you built
and excited to talk about it today so
let's just kick off what is the
subscription value Loop calculator sure
yeah well first of all benchmarks very
polarizing topic super controversial so
well depends if they're good or bad
meaning you true very true well that's
why they're controversial right because
a lot of them are bad but yeah so maybe
to to set some context so I think the
last time I was on this podcast a year
ago we talked about the subscription
value Loop which is basically this
framework I've developed that deposits
that the best consumer subscription
businesses are able to generate
sustainable compounding long-term growth
through three steps value creation value
delivery and value capture but the very
next question that I get from a lot of
consumer subcription leaders is okay
this this is a helpful framework in
theory but how do I actually apply it
and how can I measure the performance of
my subscription value Loop and
understand uh how I'm performing
relative to my peer set or my competitor
group and where I have the biggest
opportunities to improve and grow faster
and so the idea behind the subscription
value Loop calculator was let's compile
a set of the most important growth
benchmark marks within each of those
three steps value creation value
delivery and value capture ideally let's
enable leaders to filter it by important
variables like category and performance
tier eventually geography so that you're
making Apples to Apples comparisons and
then let's use that information to help
those growth leaders more efficiently
allocate resources against the growth
opportunities where they have the most
upside so that's the idea behind the
tool I will say right up front this is
version 1.0 and you all know this CU I
partnered with Revenue cat to build it
but I think it's already better than
pretty much everything else out there
that I've seen in terms of getting all
these metrics in one place and allowing
you to get a directionally accurate view
of your performance and you already kind
of mentioned it but where did you get
all the data for this mostly Revenue cat
and and to Jacob's Point good data great
data the best data the best you got you
wouldn't you wouldn't believe the data
we have it's great but what what other
data sources did you use and then how
did you pull it all together into the
calculator I had had this idea in my
head for some time like ever since I
came up with a framework The Next Step
had always in Theory been let's go
quantify it and let's help people look
at their data and compare it against
other companies the problem was where do
you find the data right like you need
thousands and thousands of data points
if you're if this is going to be at all
reliable right and that's part of why
there just aren't many good benchmarks
out there because there aren't very many
sources of data that are large enough
and reliable enough that you can build
accurate right like like apple and
Google's data sets well one they they're
not going to let them out and then two
like they have a bias about how they
think the world should be to serve their
needs and it's not necessarily always
100% aligned with like people building
subscription apps so totally yeah and so
this past summer I talked to Rick the
CMO revenue account and basically shared
this idea with him of you know I've got
this framework I want to quantify it I
need data in order to do that would
Revenue cap be interesting in partnering
with me and so that's what we did we
pulled data from the same data set as
the 2024 state of subscription apps
report so more than 30,000 subscription
apps that use your alls SDK I think 290
million subscribers and and almost 7
billion in subscription Revenue
represented by those apps so that's a
pretty large data set right it can
always be bigger that's a pretty good
starting point and so in partnership
with Rick and a couple other members of
the team at Revenue cat we pulled
together B1 of this subscription value
Loop calculator and we can get more into
what the specific metrics are and and
what the numbers look like but that's
where the data was sourced the one other
caveat I'll make is for the most part we
were able to get all the value creation
and value capture metrics needed from
revenue cat obviously Revenue cat
doesn't get as many of the value
delivery metrics right cost per install
cost per trial cost per subscriber
Blended acquisition cost paid
acquisition yet and so to fill that gap
for this first version we ran a one-time
survey where we ended up getting almost
600 responses across all sorts of
different geographies and categories so
it's you know it's a relatively broad
data set but much smaller sample size I
think for future versions of the product
will continue to improve on it and one
of the ways I'd like to do that is by
partnering with an MMP like apps flyer
or adjust that can fill in some of those
value delivery gaps and then we've
already started talking about it but the
next thing we should talk about is like
why benchmarks like we kind of already
talked about how bad they can be how
much the source of the benchmarks is
important but how do you think of
benchmarks as being helpful yeah I I
think where people get in trouble with
benchmarks is they try to make them the
end all Beall right they try to do more
with them than they really should be the
way I think of benchmarks is they're one
tool and a very big toolkit of things
that Founders CEOs Indie developers
product and marketing leaders individual
PMs and marketers can use to get a
directional high level view of where
they're performing better or worse than
other peers in their set and use that
information to start to hone in on where
some of their biggest strategic
opportunity areas are and where they
should be allocating more or few
resources meaning marketing dollars or
engineering bandwidth in order to more
efficiently capture value more
efficiently increase their AB test hit
rate increase the amount of impact that
their teams are delivering right but
there are a number of real limitations
to benchmarks and so a few of those are
they can be very inaccurate and
unreliable right that's the first that's
the first problem to solve for is can I
actually trust this data and if you just
go in Google or now I guess go to chat
GPT or Claud or whatever and and you put
in like what are good benchmarks for
this product you'll get something and
sometimes you'll get an answer that's
better than than other times but you
can't necessarily rely on on just
whatever metrics you find on the the LMS
are really bad at kind of like
understanding caveats and nuances uh on
these things they do a really I'll
sometimes just throw some of our like
Revenue cats core metrics in and be like
hey where's this put us and like
sometimes it's fine and it actually chat
GPT specifically is pretty good at
sighting sources sometimes like where
they got the the data from but yeah it's
it's you know it's not the most reliable
way of pulling it yeah so that's the
first order of problem is can I actually
rely on this data because if you can
it's garbage in garbage out how was it
collect you really have to kind of go
deep if you want to really understand
which isn't you know at that point you
should just go ask 10 apps you know what
I mean like the more time you spend
trying to understand the qualifications
of The Benchmark the less useful it is
yeah so first order problem is you got
to make sure they're accurate many of
them are not accurate the second order
problem is okay even if you're able to
find a reliable source of Benchmark data
often times it's too generic right some
of the largest and more reliable data
sets out there that provide subscription
app benchmarks are providing them
globally not for a specific country or
they're providing them across all app
categories not specific to health and
fitness or media and entertainment or
productivity all of which have very
different you know average metrics and
so that's the second order problem is
making sure that you're comparing Apples
to Apples and getting benchmarks that
are specific enough to be actionable and
then the third order problem is okay
even if your benchmarks are accurate and
even if they are specific enough to be
actionable they're only a jumping off
plane right they're not going to
actually tell you how to improve your
performance they're just going to tell
you where your performance is lacking
and so even in the best case scenario
they're a jumping off point and then
from there you need to apply your own
understanding of your product your
business your Target customer your
competitive set in order to make
intelligent bets on what initiatives to
pursue in order to increase your growth
one place I see people get hung up is
kind of on that third step and I think
it maybe comes to a lack of
understanding of the production process
which is kind of your first first two
points of these benchmarks which is like
looking at these things in isolation and
just being like a my trial rate I need
to do things to make my trial rate
better and like that's not what a
benchmark is telling you I mean it might
be correlated with that being a true and
correct action to take but it can't tell
you that all it can tell you is like for
this measure assuming you get the like
systematics of it correct here's what
this measure is and where it puts you in
the distribution and I think sometimes
what people do is they fail to think
about the process like the inputs that
led to that which can be even within a
category can be like nature of your app
like who you're in that c subcategory
like what's your differentiator and
folks can just like dive in on like oh I
got to fix sub I got to fix like a
conversion rate or churn this is one
where like I've seen a lot of people
maybe spend too much time on retention
which like sounds like you should oh
retention people look at the model and
they go like oh it's one over if I get
just perfect retention I'll be a
trillionaire and there are physics
limitations right to like how far you
can push that which I think that's where
good use of metrics if you can like
understand what that particular
percentile means for you can guide you
to maybe be like okay I can back off on
this because like I've maybe hit sort of
like the low hanging fruit but that's
often where I see people they lose the
forc through the trees right they see
like one thing and they like over obsess
about it and then they get frustrated
because they're like oh yeah we worked
on our trial start rate for two years
and you know we went from 10% to 12%
which maybe that's significant but like
there might have been other things you
could do to like really push the
business there's almost the midwit meme
here of like on the one end of the
spectrum it's like just build a good
product and then on the other end of the
spectrum you've got the Jedi Master and
it's just build a really good product
and then in the middle it's like I'm
going to look at a 100 different metrics
and I'm going to optimize every last
thing so this gets to like the
double-edge sort of benchmarks right I
think they can be a very effective tool
in your toolkit ultimately you have to
pair the science of the data and the
metrics that you're using for the
benchmarks with the art of I'm going to
apply my own intuition to understand why
I'm seeing variances in certain places
and then the next question is okay I'm
seeing these variances is this a gap
that I can fill based off of improved
product experience or improved marketing
or actually know how to fix it yeah or
or is it a gap that's exogenous because
for example I'm a dating app and so I'm
going to have high turn rates because if
I have a good product people are
naturally turning off the platform or is
it inherent to the business model too
like if you're a freemium app by
definition your trial start rate is
likely to be lower if you're premium you
probably shouldn't even do a free trial
and so you're looking at some of these
benchmarks and you have to analyze it
through the lens of like the business
you've created and how you want to
operate your business you can go hard
pay wall that'll juice your trial start
right but like is that what you're
optimizing for it's like you need to
understand them through how you run your
business and how you want like how
you're trying to grow your business and
what you want your business to become
I'm sure we've talked about this
probably Phil in the past but like the
Dutch damn analogy right of like you
stick your finger in one hole and then
another hole is going to pop open right
and it's not it's not so binary but
there is this also this interl nature
that often by pushing on one of these
benchmarks you're going to affect the
others and you have to like keep that in
mind as well the best thing you can
learn at least this talking for me like
looking at B2B benchmarks and stuff like
that I think is it's just to like give
you directional Insight right I think
it's which is your point you were making
before Phil it's like feed it with your
intuition also and and maybe this is uh
as I I I'll say move progressively to
the left on the midwit meme over time
I'm just like more and more let me just
do what do what do what feels good and
feels right and then if it tracks to a
metric like that's great I'll draw from
my own experience here so when I was
leading product growth at Quizlet there
were basically two ways I went about
trying to find benchmarks the first was
the one we talked about earlier which is
go on Google at the time there was no
chat GPT or or Claude but go on Google
or find some other publicly available
source of information and just ask
what's a good Benchmark that was very
fast and easy and Broad but unreliable
for me it was the um ser series B ever
note series B deck that everybody used
that was like the only consumer
subscriptions silver lining in 2014 or
whatever yeah so but it's like bucket
one find broad overly generic publicly
available
resources fast easy not particularly
reliable the second bucket was on the
complete other end of the Spectrum which
is like I had my network of other
product leaders PMS marketers at you
know given quiz was an education company
CH course hero photo maath du Lang
and so we would periodically jump on a
call or just sort of compare notes at a
high level on hey roughly what's the
band of what we can reasonably expect
for something like signup rate trial
start rate trial conversion rate average
revenue per user LTV but then you get
into another problem which is one a lot
of the even within education right you
have lots of different flavors of
products and so it's still can be pretty
apples and oranges the other problem is
if you're two apples to apples you're
obviously not going to share sensitive
data and information because then you're
sharing data with direct competitors I
think this is something I mean I don't
want to keep Jing us off the off the
trail here but I think this something
people unless you're like in a dead heat
with somebody on like fighting over like
individual user acquisition spend it's
like what's somebody going to do if they
know your trial star rate is lower than
theirs like how is that possibly going
to like change their which is one of the
cool things in consumer subscriptions I
think is like when you are competing and
there are some like Secret Sauce things
around this stuff but a lot of times you
can also nine times out of 10 you can
just go look and copy what your
competitor so it's not like it's not
like there's anything secret that like
is is able to be hidden right unless
you're using some crazy modeling or
something like this to acquire users
it's good creative it's good app good
creative good strategy like there's no
super secret sauce right anyway sorry
sidebar now that we've totally thrown
benchmarks under the bus we've got a
whole rest of the podcast to talk about
should we just not do Sosa let's just
we'll figure something else out let me
take a stab at framing the rest of our
conversation I was actually writing this
morning I don't know if this will turn
into a tweet or blog post but the whole
ideas versus execution has always really
bugged me and I haven't ever been able
to like fully put my finger on it I
think this morning I came to like a
piece with the idea and here's the thing
what we hand waving call execution is
really judgment it's like there's a ton
of ideas ideas are a dime a dozen but
inherently
good ideas aren't a dime a dozen like
there are good ideas and so what
execution really is like great execution
isn't just doing work isn't being good
at programming or good at marketing it's
a filtering of ideas into the good ideas
and then executing on those and so I
think what we can talk about with the
subscription value Loop calculator and
where benchmarks can add value is as an
input to your judgment not as like a
decision maker not as as the end all be
all but as one of many inputs into your
judgment of which idea is good which
idea is bad I mean if you listen to sub
Club podcast you're going to get a
million ideas of like oh we should do
this on our pay wall we should do that
on our onboarding and like you can't
execute on all of those and so the great
products and the great product leaders
are the ones who have the judgment to
actually pick which ideas are good and
then go execute on that and I think the
calculator and the benchmarks can be a
good input into those judgment DEC
decisions those millions of small
decisions you make along a product
Journey so that's why the subcription
value calculator go look at it and bring
it up while you listen to the rest of
this podcast and make better judgments
along the way I think that's exactly
right it's both working on good ideas
but also working on good ideas that are
targeted at the right problems and
that's where a lot of companies get in
trouble is there are startups they have
limited resources and so in some cases
they're executing on good ideas but
they're good ideas focused on the wrong
problems which aren't where they have
the biggest upside and so they don't see
a lot of impact from it or they're
focusing on good ideas that are good
ideas two years from now that aren't
good ideas today as a startup sure I
guess that you could put that under
judgment but that's also just like
entrepreneurial like wisdom or like just
focus and good at resource alloc I mean
resource allocation is really the game
and like that can be other people that
could be at the beginning you right
individual time and attention and
dollars but I'll um oppose or or throw a
Counterpoint here to like have like
picking good ideas and that I think this
kind of feeds into the topic but that
like I think even the best idea Pickers
in the world have like 51% hit rate you
know what I mean or like they barely
exceed the median of what everybody else
does in terms of like that execution bit
it's like you need to have that edge of
judgment but then you just need to have
like consistent application right
because that edge will compound if your
competitors or your ERS are only making
choices 50% of the time that are correct
and you're doing 51 each cycle each
cycle is a 1% compounding advantage and
then also if you can shorten your cycle
time that's another like linear increase
in your growth rate in terms of like
Discovery and sounds very esoteric I
promise this is like related to like how
to use benchmarks and things like this
and determine like each day like what is
the action we're going to take today to
actually move the business forward I
think we keep selling and anti- selling
this this concept but like because I
think the Trap that we're trying to like
tell people to avoid is that you can
very easily bury the advantages of these
benchmarks and like good data- driven
decision by like delaying decision-
making as well right like often if you
spend too much time trying to pick the
perfect decision you've quickly like
eliminated any advantage of a great
decision by not doing anything right
next thing I wanted to talk through is
how you apply the subscription value
Loop you know you run a Consulting
business you talk to a ton of apps about
their business you help them make
decisions via data via judgment via
shooting from the hip but you help make
decisions and so that's kind of the next
place I wanted to go with this is like
how do you use this tool how do you use
benchmarks to help make better decisions
in the companies that you work with yeah
it's a great question and usually this
is a tool that I use right at the outset
in the first week or two when I'm
engaging with new client and and
onboarding and getting to understand
their business better and there's a few
advantages of that I mean one is it's
just a good forcing function to get all
of the most important growth metrics for
the business in one place and some
clients I work with are very
sophisticated and they've already got
all of this organized they've got a
growth model they've got their mix panel
their amplitude dashboard and
everything's dialed in other clients
especially some of the earlier stage
clients I work with or IND developers
this may be the first time that they're
pulling some of these metrics together
and sort of seeing how all the dots
connect and so that's one advantage of
doing it right away the other Advantage
for me is it's just a really efficient
way for me to get up and running quickly
and get the sort of quick diagnosis of
where are the biggest bottlenecks in the
company's growth engine and where might
there be some quick- win opportunities
to start putting points on the board
it's almost like x-ray vision into where
is the biggest problem in the loop is it
value creation are they not actually
creating a product that is resonating
with users is it value delivery are they
not being efficient about acquiring
those users or is it value capture
they've got a great product and they're
acquiring users efficiently but they're
not actually converting anybody into
subscribers or their price is too low
they're not getting enough Revenue back
per subscriber and so it's usually a
diagnostic tool that I use in those
first two weeks we don't spend a ton of
time on it honestly it's like I share
the tool with the client and in a 1-hour
call we pull a lot of the metrics into
the dashboard and we sort of see the
heat map of where the biggest gaps and
opportunities are and then I go off and
do some additional analysis at a more
granular level to figure out what some
of the highest priority growth
initiatives might be for us to work on
together having done this with a bunch
of clients now and and having worked on
the calculator for months and months and
written a blog post about it and all
that other stuff do you have any like
kind of key takeaways or insights that
are examples of like what you might want
to learn from putting your data in the
subscription value Loop yeah sure one
relatively recent example there's an
edtech client that I've been working
with where as I said in the first week
we sort of dug into the tool put a bunch
of the metrics in and one thing that
became very apparent was subscriber
retention was really strong right so
they had a product that was resonating
with users they were able to retain
their subscribers over a long period of
time better than even the 75th
percentile of Education apps let alone
the average but their biggest issues
were number one their subscriber
conversion rates were quite low and
number two their pricing was higher than
the typical edtech app in their category
and then the third problem they were
facing was their paid advertising
efficiency was lower than you would hope
to see and some of that was being driven
by a price that was a little too high
and an onboarding flow and a pay wall
that wasn't fully optimized right and so
those metrics didn't tell the whole
story but they gave me sort of a map of
where we might begin to explore
opportunities how do we improve new user
onboarding to convert more free users
into trilers how do we improve the pay
wall to maximize the excitement of those
new trilers and ultimately convert them
into subscribers and then how do we
optimize pricing in order to make sure
that people are more willing to pay for
the subscription once their trial is
over and so that basically laid out the
road map for the first three months of
our engagement and there were a number
of wins that came out of new user
onboarding optimization payall
optimization and then we ran a
subscription survey that confirmed a lot
of the same stuff that we had seen in
the subscription value calculator but
got into a lot more detail on the
specifics of what needed to change in
order to shore up some of those metrics
yeah any other examples before we move
on to the talking through a spreadsheet
on a podcast yeah a couple more examples
so there's a fitness product that I've
worked with in the past that ran into a
very common challenge that consumer
subscription apps run into particularly
in the fitness category I know Strava
has run into this issue which is giving
way too much value for free right and so
the way that that was showing up in the
metrics was their price was relatively
low compared to their peer set and their
subscriber conversion rates were
relatively low and you could interpret
that a lot of different ways on its face
but again we ran a subscription survey
we got into the weeds around what both
free users and subscribers were saying
about their free value promise their
premium value promise and one of the
insights that came out of it was the
free product is so good do I actually
need to pay for the premium product and
what is my willingness to pay for that
premium product and so again it didn't
give us the full picture of exactly what
we needed to go do but it told us where
we should be focusing our resources
awesome well let's dive into the
calculator then some of you may be
listening in the car on a walk or
whatever pulling up the calculator at
some point or listening and then going
to pull it up would be super helpful to
help all of this make sense but the
first thing I wanted to go through was
in the calculator you have several
things that the person needs to input
it's like you have to put in some
metrics and I want to kind of go through
those and like why you included those
and kind of the importance of them in
the calculator kind of helping to build
that map of where opportunities might
lie I'll lay out sort of the 30,000 foot
view of how the tool works and then we
can drill into whatever details you guys
are most excited to talk about but at a
high level I mean one of the
requirements for me with a tool like
this is it needed to be simple so it's a
single spreadsheet you go in there's a
column where you enter a couple dozen
metrics usually I recommend that
companies enter the average across their
last 12 months worth of data just
because if you have any seasonality in
your business or if there are other sort
of Peaks and valleys a Year's worth of
data can help to smooth that out
obviously the caveat would be if you had
a major change to your pay wall or your
pricing or some other big variable that
could affect the metrics within the last
12 months just be careful about how that
could influence the metrics but
otherwise look at the last 12 months
take the average performance over the
last 12 months input that into the
column that's your company's data and
then you select the category of app
you're in so health and fitness media
and entertainment photo and video
productivity there there are 11
different categories or you can just
look at all categories combined and the
second filter is performance tier so you
can look at the 25th percentile the 50th
percentile the 75th percentile or the
95th percentile of apps in terms of how
they perform and
that can be helpful as a proxy for your
stage right if you're an indie developer
that's just getting started I would say
focus on p50 you want it be aiming for
be better than average if you're already
a venture funded startup and you know
you feel like you've got a pretty strong
product already you probably want to
focus on p75 or even P95 so that's the
second filter you can use and then once
you've put in your app category your
performance tier and your business
metrics the tool immediately outputs
your performance Delta relative to your
peer set and it shows you a heat map in
red versus green in terms of where
you're over underperforming and so
pretty quickly within a few hours of
doing this exercise you've got a very
basic road map of hey where are we over
and underperforming and where might it
make sense for us to make strategic bets
once people have done all that and
they're looking at the Heat Map There's
a bunch of different sections that
you're going to get this heat map Delta
and the first section is about LTV CAC
payback period kind of th those top of
funnel met tricks and so I wanted to
dive into those and it's so tricky you
know Blended versus paid you know how
much are you spending are you more
organic driven like all of these things
are going to factor in so how do you
think about that first section around
payback period LTV to CAC is that
Blended CAC is that only paid CAC how do
you figure all that out so the way I
look at LTB over CAC ratio and payback
period is there's sort of good
barometers over the overall health of
the business uh the strength of the unit
omics and the efficiency of the
company's growth engine right and so
you're not going to be able to
prioritize a road map for your product
or marketing team based on these metrics
but you'll get a good overall sense for
the company's performance and so to me
LTV over CAC and payback period are the
outputs of this tool they're what's
telling you okay if you want a Target
LTV overc of 3x which is sort of the
gold standard for Consumer apps and you
want a payback period of ideally fewer
than 3 months or even within the first
month how are you performing relative to
those targets and relative to the
targets of your peer set in your
category and then underneath that you
have the three sections in the
subscription value Loop so you have
value creation value delivery and value
capture and each of those steps have
their own component metrics that drive
those steps in the loop that are
ultimately leading to the output of LTB
over CAC and payback period so when I
look at the tool I'm looking first at
LTB overc and payback period to say on
the whole how is this company performing
versus its Peet and then if they're over
underperforming the next question is why
like where are the bottlenecks what are
the specific metrics where the company
is most underperforming that we can go
focus on First and so then I drill down
into value creation which is measuring
how effectively the company is creating
value for users value delivery which
measures how efficiently they're
acquiring users and subscribers and
value capture which looks at how
efficiently they're monetizing those
users I do want to talk more about LTV
toac and Blended versus non all that but
we can get into that in the value
delivery section of the data but the
first section is the value creation and
there's a few metrics there there's sign
up rate you discuss this in the blog
post and we were discussing this before
starting the podcast is that what you
mean by that is registration rate how
many people actually register because
most apps these days are going to have
some kind of registration wall where you
want to collect an email you want them
to create an account I mean you know I
have not done that in my dinky side
project apps and have regretted it for a
decade now and I still it's not
something I fixed yet but most apps if
you're trying to build a real business
you need that's like the most that's
what I tell people too but like it's
like the meanest neg be like yeah if
you're trying to build a real business I
mean if we're just playing around here
then then don't have a sign up but like
we were I was asking Phil about it
because I didn't exactly know what it is
and this is one of the pieces of data
that doesn't come from us doesn't come
from revenue cat because like you we
don't we have some distinctions around
sign up versus not but this is this is
from the survey data correct yeah this
is one of the metrics from the survey
data it's basically account registration
rate so what percentage of installs are
converting into registered users and
it's not directly feeding LTB over CAC
ratio and payback period but it's an
important proxy metric that's further
Upstream right because in most cases if
you haven't registered an account it's
very unlikely that you're going to pay
for a subscription which is ultimately
what's driving Revenue yeah and then if
you don't have their email you can't win
them back if they don't sign up you
can't do so many of the other parts of
value delivery and value capture if you
don't have their attention so and I I
think you know you you'd mention that
activation rate like I is really the
metric you would want to have in this
report because you want an activated
user whether they sign up for an account
or not I mean we just said is important
but what you really want is somebody
who's like experienced the value
somebody who's activated but like it's
that's so fuzzy it's so I mean sign up a
sign up could be an activation it just
it depends on how you define it right
well this goes back to what we were
talking about as far as the reliability
of data right activation rate would be a
great metric for this tool the reason we
haven't included it so far is because
the activation metric across different
products looks so different right and so
it's really hard to compare apples to
apples and so for that reason signup
rate or account registration rate is a
good enough proxy for are we getting
enough installs to take that first step
of creating an account and then you
start to get into the other value
creation metrics which are mostly around
retention right so both for monthly and
annual subscribers what is month one
month 2 month 3 month 6 month 12
retention rate what is year 1 and year 2
annual retention rate and then that data
can be used to calculate an average
lifetime for both monthly and annual
subscribers which is obviously critical
for driving those LTV overc and payback
period measures yeah which is an
interesting way of collecting the data
and like actually looking at it not just
looking at my Blended monthly because
that has a lot of effects on cohort
composition but then also stretching
that out a little bit to 1 three one 123
62 which gives you know some apps have
really fast drop off some apps have
later drop off and like that's probably
a super good example of a case where you
need to really apply context to know
like if you have a six-month drop off or
one month drop off that's higher or
lower than bench probably has more to do
with the nature of your app right and
like the sort of cyclical Natures or or
seasonalities and things like that but
it's good to bring that in rather than
you have this metric later on that that
feeds in which is the the monthly
average monthly periods which also we
were talking earlier it's like a tricky
one because to calculate to have a true
understanding of because that number
tends to float and have biases based on
like you know amount of time you've been
collecting data but you can put in a
rough idea that is helpful in terms of
estimating LTV but yeah I guess like
Phil when you pull in that curve what
are some of the um conditions you might
look at there to be like oh we should
maybe this customer needs to do X or Y
like if they have like short-term drop
off or like maybe long-term drop off
like are there are there examples you
can think of where there's some
interesting variants well one very
interesting example I'll give you is I
had a client I looked at somewhat
recently where annual subscriber
retention rate was much better than
monthly subscriber retention rate and
obviously in general you're going to get
longer retention from anual versus
monthly subscribers mostly because of
you know if you've got 50 bucks to drop
you're probably just a stickier customer
period it's always been kind of my
assumption for that but yeah they're
higher intent users and they've
committed more upfront but even relative
to benchmarks right relative to their
peer set their annual subscriber
retention outperform their peer set but
their monthly subscriber reten
underperform their peer set and then
combining that with an Insight from the
value capture component of the tool
which was that their annual subscription
price was higher than their peer set the
Insight was we should look at our annual
subscription price relative to monthly
and potentially offer a more generous
annual subscription discount and we
should run additional optimizations on
our pay wall to try to nudge more users
from monthly into annual subscription
plans because we know that if we get a
user to convert into an annual plan and
we are significantly outperforming our
peer set on annual subscriber retention
but the opposite is true for monthly and
so there is a lot of upside even more so
than the normal upside to converting
more users into annual subscriptions and
so you can start to see how some of
these pieces fit together right it is
hard talking about a spreadsheet on a
podcast but you can see how the pieces
fit together and how it leads to
actionable next steps a company can take
based off of the numbers you're seeing
this is when I wanted to dive into some
of the caveats though I was talking to
an app recently that has below median
retention rates I think their annual
retention rate was something like
30% but they're driving a ton they're
driving most of their traffic through
paid ads and they're getting like day 45
return on ad spend I think this is like
you know what business are you in what
business are you building how are you
operating your business and when you see
that and you think okay that's where we
need to focus like we got to get
retention higher yes
but the way you're running the business
and being able to get that 30-day return
on ad spin 45 day return on ad spend
you're inherently bringing in a lot more
people and lower intent
users and man if you're retaining 30%
and you're getting 45 day Raz like you
can stack those cohorts over time this
brings up another great point which is
this is oversimplifying things but
there's a little bit of a dichotomy I've
seen between earlier stage consumer
subscription businesses in some cases
indd developers that have built really
efficient engines at rapidly converting
fre users into subscribers making sure
their d45 Raz or even their like in
opel's case d8 Raz is really really
efficient right and so they are printing
money in the short term and that's great
that's a great small business but then
on the other end of the spectrum you
have the larger consumer subscription
businesses that are trying to get to
hundreds of millions if if not billions
of dollars in evaluation right it's a
much smaller ecosystem but that's where
what got you to Greatness on the first
category won't get you to Greatness on
the second cat right if you're shooting
for one of those really big Grand Slams
then just having really efficient d8 or
d45 row ads won't get you there because
you need to find ways to continue to
grow organically so that you're not
overring on paid ads spin to begin with
you need to find ways to increase
subscriber retention because that's the
foundation for everything else right and
so this is where one of the other
filters we want to add to this tool is
company stage because if you're a seed
stage or series a startup by all means
focus on just being really efficient at
acquiring users early on and making sure
you're getting fast payback periods but
if you're a serc startup and you're
shooting for a billion dollar valuation
and eventually going public you have to
look at the metrics in totally different
ways you're not going to get there with
30% it takes too many years I don't
think it's it's possible because what
happens is as you scale that right
you're going to hit you're going to
expire those users and like because you
didn't build a reliable and and and the
corollary to what you were just saying
Phil like seed Wise It's is like what
game are you playing right like what's
your game I've seen seen this it's not
necessarily A Bad Thing to be like yeah
let's rush to get some sort of engine of
something here because CU often that can
be the chip that or like the sort of
Lifeline you need to then like worry
about the next stage double-sided sword
again sometimes you can get in there and
then you get stuck with this like sort
of suboptimal local like that you get
stuck in and now you've maybe traded in
some brand that's hard to like recover
and things like that but again depends
on the game depends on the game you're
playing so but if you're spending off
cash to Phil's Point earlier then it's
easier to kind of make those next
Investments right exactly yeah you earn
the right to kind of be like okay like
how do we actually reinvest I mean
that's how businesses historically not
using outside capitals you generate some
free cash flow through some positive
roas and then you can reinvest that in
R&D and like other things like that that
that can ideally like I mean the comment
about gears right but it's like you
start in first gear and it's maybe just
like this rapid sort of just get some
money back and then okay great we've
expired we've topped out in first gear
and now we have to think about okay
what's second gear like how do we like
increase our leverage and actually go a
little bit further and that will change
right this is why this is not a like do
once and forget sort of thing so maybe
we should we should jump I want to keep
us moving but maybe we should jump on to
like sort of the value delivery the
inputs to this because I think this is
this is interesting you talk about like
cost per install and it made me think
about like Revenue CAD system is
different but like when I think about
CPI or like cost of acquisition or
whatever I just take bit like number of
installs which be for us like a sign up
and I just divide it by my entire sales
and marketing budget so I'm curious like
how do you suggest people like kind of
put together a rough number for that is
it very inclusive or is it just like
literally like how much should I spend
on Facebook the way I think about this
is there's sort of aggregate cost per
install and so that can be across all of
your different paid acquisition channels
and can also include organic acquisition
right so you're taking an overall
Blended cost per install and that's
what's most helpful for looking at the
summary metrics of LTV over CAC and
payback period as an entire business but
then if I'm a performance marketer and I
want to evaluate the efficiency of my
individual Performance Marketing
channels Facebook Instagram Tik Tok
Google whatever the case might be then
I'm looking at a very different set of
metrics which is my paid cost per
install through each of those individual
channels so that I can compare the
efficiency across all of them but you
have to look at them like they're so
useful in relatives with each other
because like and this is where
benchmarks break down as you zoom in
right because like you know other people
what they consider a cost per install a
cost per X may or may not be like includ
you know do that you include your own
salary right if you're a performance
marketer do you know what I mean that
might be a bigger question for like
Founders and stuff to determine how they
do stuff my two cents would be if you're
trying and I think Phil with the the
vision of this is is to be very high
level so if I were you I would I would
probably include whoever's working on
day-to-day ad creative all that stuff
that's probably like all should go in
maybe not if you're just like trying to
evaluate a model for just trying to like
as you said on the Performance Marketing
like rip a big you know ad spend and
make sure you're making that money back
and it stays above the line or whatever
but if you're actually thinking about
running a business you probably should
be considering those costs as well you
know I think that gives for a better
Blended metric too because the whole
idea of the Blended metric is that
you're accounting for organic so if
somebody's like you know creating Tik
Tok videos and you're not putting money
behind them it's not part of your paid
spend but you're paying for those
installs so if you have 20 people
creating organic Tik toks like that's
marketing spend that's pay so what do
you consider like a cost of organic I
think there's two different ways of
looking at this depending on what your
goal is like if you are the VP of
finance and you want to understand
exactly where all the dollars and cents
are going then absolutely you want to
find a way to load in the cost of your
marketing team or the cost of your sales
team in the case of a B2B business but
if you're looking at the health of the
business in terms of the unit economics
then generally you're not going to layer
in sgna cost because you want to focus
on per dollar of marketing spend how
many users are you getting back and the
reason for that is as you scale into a
larger and larger company then the
percentage of your cost basis that's
coming from things like a marketer's
salary gets to be a smaller and smaller
and smaller percentage and so the way
I've built this tool it's very much
focused on the unit economics so I'm not
looking at the cost of the sales and
marketing team in these value delivery
metrics I'm looking at the Blended
average cost per install cost per trial
and cost per subscriber when you look at
users you're requiring organically that
could be through vir Word of Mouth it
could be through posts on social media
but installs trials and subscribers you
aren't directly spending marketing
dollars on averaged against your paid
marketing spent across which which I
guess actually is maybe the inverse of
the question of using these benchmarks
correctly again which is like because at
a smaller scale
and which you want to be careful of and
what I mean there is like you have to
think about what is your actual motion
and like what percentage and of your
efforts and energies because that's what
ultimately you're trying to do is like
get some insight about how you should
invest that incremental energy and like
where is that falling now on these
inputs and and they might actually be
correlated but you're right like at
scale these systems are leveraged right
so one performance marketer can do you
know 10K a month and add been 100K and a
million probably with a similar amount
of head count potentially exactly right
yeah as you get larger and larger
what really matters is your marketing
budget more and more so versus the cost
of your marketing team and so the tool
is meant to look at it from a unit
economic standpoint how do you think
about kind of bringing it back to the
earlier section how do you think about
payback period and customer acquisition
cost in relation to all these things and
then especially kind of the blend
between paid and organic as well because
I think for some companies who have
amazing organic and start spending on
paid it's easy to look at the Blended
and then let those payback periods
extend further and further out into time
because the money is just rolling in
because you have such great organic base
but how do you think about balancing all
those things of like how much you spend
what you expect of your spend versus
what you expect of your organic and how
do you balance all those things I think
the most efficient way to answer that is
it goes back to the science and the Art
of interpreting benchmarks like this so
if you look at your value delivery
metrics and you see that you're very
very efficient on cost per install cost
per trial and cost per subscriber there
are a few different reasons that could
be driving that one is you're getting
the vast majority of your acquisition
through organic you might be really
really inefficient at paid marketing but
that's being offset by a huge percentage
of your users and subscribers coming
through organic channels so that's one
possibility a second possibility is sort
of the opposite you're getting a good
number of your users and subscribers
from Paid channels but you're you've got
a really good performance marketing team
and you're really really efficient at
acquiring those users and there are a
few other flavors of of what could be D
numers like that and so you start with
the science which is like let me look at
the numbers and let me look at where I'm
over and underperforming but then you
got to get into interpreting why is this
the case and so another example I'll
give you of a client I've worked with
where we specifically looked at these
value delivery metrics was they were
acquiring a significant percentage of
their users through paid channels so
they were very very efficient if you
looked at their paid cost per install
cost per trial cost per subscriber you
know they would have been among the best
in class at acquiring users through
Facebook but were over reliant on paid
acquisition spend overall in terms of
acquiring users relative to organic and
so one of the first things that I worked
on with that client was figuring out how
to get them off of the drug of paid
acquisition and how to acquire more
users through word of mouth or SEO or
other non-paid channels that's a a great
example and I mean even my own app I
mean you know I have this side project
weather app I talk about in the podcast
a bit I haven't spent any money on paid
acquisition this year I made like 100k
so my uh you know if I plug those
numbers in my LTV to CAC is incred
incredible it's amazing nothing else
again goes back to my point nothing else
went into making that 100K happen at all
you know it was just free money but yeah
so everybody has to figure out kind of
what business they're building how
they're going to build it why the blend
that they're seeing why the numbers make
sense and how they want to move forward
from that so great context for all of
that when you're an early stage startup
number one you're going to get more
hopefully you're able to get more user
acquisition organically than you will
once you start to get beyond your early
adopters and you have to start paying
more more money to acquire users because
they're just lower intent you're outside
of your ideal customer profile and then
the second thing is across all of the
other metrics value creation and value
capture early adopters tend to
outperform the later majority right and
so what that means is you have to
interpret these metrics through the lens
of is this sustainable and so to use
your example David like if you're an
India developer an early stage startup
and the vast majority of your
acquisition is organic and so your LTV
over CAC is like to the Moon that's
great in the here and now but it won't
last like eventually if scale to a
certain size history tells us every
consumer subscription business at some
point is going to hit a point where they
have to spend more and more dollars on
Performance Marketing in order to
sustain growth if that's what they want
to do and so it's another great example
of where you have to apply your own
intuition and looking at this data and
projecting ahead to how the numbers are
likely to change as you scale yeah so
let's talk about that next section value
captures you've gotten the person in the
app you need to monetize them so let's
talk through some of the metrics there
yeah and I actually I've said this
before I think value capture is is of
the three steps in the subscription
value I actually think it's the one that
most often gets overlooked right because
especially early stage companies you
have a lot of product driven Founders
they want to overd deliver value for
their customers and so they're
rightfully so investing a lot of their
resources into just building a great
product and getting people to talk about
it but at some point you have to capture
resources back from your best users who
are generally your subscribers in order
to reinvest into the business and keep
growing and so value capture is all
about that it's all about converting fre
users into subscribers and so it looks
at both how efficient you are are at
converting users through the
subscription funnel trial start rate
trial conversion rate and install the
paid conversion rate it also looks at
what your pricing looks like so what is
your annual monthly subscription price
right now I don't have Weekly
subscription plans in the tool that's
another thing we could add in the future
but it looks at your price for each of
your different subscription plans and
tiers and then it also looks at things
like your subscription plan mix so what
percentage of your subscriptions are
annual versus monthly and your gross
margins like how much of the Topline
Revenue that you're getting per
subscription are you actually retaining
as a business after you've paid things
like app store fees one of the things
that I really want to do at some point
maybe like uh state of subscription to
app report 2027 when we've got like 10
data scientists and a whole team around
this and version five of the
subscription value Loop calculator is
that I would love to do a full funnel
Benchmark because when you get to this
stage and you're starting to say oh well
my trial start rate's really low but
then your trial conversion rate is
amazing and so overall your trial open
to paid is really high but your trial
start rate's really low I think if we
were able to like do full funnel
benchmarks and like look at the apps
that have you know higher stats here and
then going all the way through retention
not just looking at subscriber
acquisition but actually going all the
way to you know two three years down the
road and then that's where you start to
see the benchmarks like very few people
are going to be P95 on every single
metric along the entire chain usually
you're going to have a strength
somewhere in the chain that you're the
real outlier in that and that makes the
business work even if you're below
Benchmark on another metric that's a
great call out and and you see that
anecdotally with a lot of the top
consumer subscription apps in different
categories right it's not like they're
P95 across every single metric in fact
it'd be really hard to do that because
by definition if you're really really
efficient at converting free users and
subscribers you're probably have a
harder time retaining them because
you're getting some lower intent users
into your subscription funnel similarly
if you you know really if your prices
are really really high so you're in the
highest percentile on how much revenue
you're getting per subscriber that might
negatively impact your ability to
convert subscribers in the first place
so there's sort of natural checks and
balances on some of these metrics I
think the important thing and what I
generally tell my clients is ideally
you're finding a way to be good enough
across the majority of these metrics you
don't want to have too many areas where
you have glaring deficiencies again
there are outliers like dating apps
where you're going to naturally have
higher turn rates that's part of why you
have the category filter but you want to
do your best to be within Striking
Distance of at least average if not p75
across as many of these metrics as you
can be and then more often than not
there are like one or two metrics where
you are just outstanding that's where
you really outperform and so tender is a
great example of a company I teach a
case study on tender with Robbie met as
the former CPO there in my course and
tender and some of these other top
dating apps have gotten really really
good and at both converting new users
into subscribers and offering different
subscription tiers that maximize the
amount of consumer surplus they're
capturing because they know that they're
only going to be able to retain
subscribers for so long right and so
their subscription retention rates are
never going to be as good as a lot of
category leading apps and other
categories but they can make up for that
if they're really really efficient at
capturing value from users in their
first 3 to six months the other lens I
think to think through this section with
is stage as well which you brought up
earlier is that you know I think
dualingo is a good example I have gone
through their Q10 and and looked at
their publicly shared stats to try and
verify this but I would assume they're
like app open or their sign up rate
their activation rate to subscriber rate
historically has been on the lower side
because they've they're driving a ton of
usage in that premium tier and they've
built up this massive premium base well
what are they doing now as a public
company worth1 billion dollar that's now
their opportunity to improve on that the
massive free user base to start
monetizing them better through ads
through converting into subscriptions
through other methods but then also to
get better and better at converting new
free users coming in into paid
subscribers so there's also like a Time
component of this it's like you know du
lingo is obviously like P95 and several
key metrics and then the areas where
they're not good is like now at 1010
billion doll valuation there's a lot of
Leverage for them to pull to get better
at those I think that's exactly right
and if you look at how dual product has
evolved over the last few years a lot of
people don't know this like dualingo
spent the first 5 years as a company
focused exclusively on the free user
experience so they launched in I think
it was 2011 or 2012 they didn't
introduce their dual lingo Plus
subscription until 2017 so they didn't
start monetizing their user base really
at all you know the the Elevate story
right we were doing brain training apps
that were paid up front and then
dualingo came out that that's kind of
and then it was like okay we can't win
that they did a really good job of
turning Venture Capital into like a
monopoly essentially yeah it becomes a
real competitive mode at some point but
then at this point dualingo is a really
large company right they're worth over10
billion now and so the cost of acquiring
incremental users gets higher and higher
they fight against that by creating a
better and better and better product and
now they're expanding into math and
music and so that's unlocking early
adopters in new categories but still on
the whole they're having to expend more
resources to acquire the marginal
customer which means they have to get
more efficient about capturing value
from their subscribers or from their
free users and so if you look at
dualingo now they're adding more ads to
the free user experience that means
they're increasing the LTV of
nonsubscribers it also means that
they're able to nudge more free users
into subscribers because they get
annoyed at the advertisements and so
they they they'll say fine enough is
enough I'll pay for dualingo Plus or do
or dualingo Max and so you can sort of
see that strategy playing out in their
product Evolution so I did want to give
you a chance to talk briefly about the
future of the value Loop calculator I
know you've got some stuff in the works
and the 2025 report will be out soon and
you're going to incorporate that data
into the calculator so it'll be updated
in the relatively near future any other
updates top of mind yeah well first of
all I do want to thank I know this is a
revenue cat podcast but I do want to
thank Rick and the rest of the team at
Revenue cat that helped pull this first
version of the tool together like
without the data set the tool wouldn't
exist that was a great experience and
I'm really excited to partner with you
all again next year once the 20125 state
of subscription apps report is ready to
do V2 I think a number of things that
will happen with V2 I mean the first and
most obvious one is you guys are growing
quickly and so the sample size of apps
is just going to keep getting larger and
larger I think it was 30,000 apps for
this first version I it will be a larger
number for v2 I think that the second
thing we want to do is add more filters
right so I mentioned before just how
critical it is to compare apples to
apples and make sure that you're looking
at apps within your category within your
performance tier but you also ideally
want to be able to look at apps within
your geography right we know that us
users tend to monetize at higher rates
than International users but they're
also more expensive to acquire so being
able to cut by US versus Europe versus
Japan South Korea and a couple other
geographies would be a great filter IDE
eventually getting to the point where we
can filter by iOS versus Android or even
versus web would be another filter I'm
really excited to add and then these
will probably be more difficult but
eventually being able to filter by
company stage and a couple of other
variables would would be great to do as
well and then the last thing what we
talked about a little bit earlier was
there are a couple of weaknesses in this
first MVP version of the tool right the
biggest one being that those value
delivery metrics are coming from a
survey they're not coming from the data
in rbat SDK and so either finding ways
to get that data from revenue cat or
finding another partner like appsflyer
or adjust that can pull in the value
delivery metric data awesome that I'm
really looking forward to the future of
this calculator and uh I think you know
internally at Revenue cat we've been
talking about more and more ways we can
help even in our dashboard kind of
surface aspects of this to like help
developers spot areas of weakness and
things like that so looking forward to
your work and looking forward to what we
can do to to productize aspects of these
ideas but anything else you want to
share as we're wrapping up I know you
actually have a new live course
launching in January right yeah just a
few things so number one if you're
interested in learning more about the
work I do I have a website it's just
Phil G carter.com and I'm at philg
Carter across substack LinkedIn and x
and so if you're interested in the blog
post I wrote on subscription value Loop
or the subscription value Loop
calculator you can check that out at
Phil garter on substack you mentioned
the course so I do have a live course
that I now teach on Maven the next court
actually launching in mid January and so
you can check out consumer sub growth
course at maven.com and actually if you
use promo code subclub I'm offering a
10% discount um so feel free feel free
to use that and then lastly is you know
my core business is being a full-time
growth adviser and angel investor at
this point and so I work with about half
a dozen different clients at a time I'm
at full capacity right now but I'll
likely have capacity opening up in q1
next year and so if you're interested in
potentially working together on uh a
more intensive basis would would love to
hear from you awesome Phil thanks so
much for joining us this was uh super
insightful and thanks of the work you're
doing in the community too like you know
we provided the data but you built the
tool and I think it's going to be super
helpful to a lot of folks and then
thanks for being so generous kind of
sharing how you use it and how to apply
it in uh building better businesses yeah
well likewise I mean I said this when I
was at the uh Revenue cat annual event
but you guys have really become thought
leaders in the community you've
aggregated this wonderful group of
people and you know it can be lonely
building apps and so having this
community of other people to compare
notes with and share data with is really
helpful and it's always a pleasure to
partner with you guys well we'll have
you back for Christmas next year I'm
sure sounds great that seems to be the
uh the timeline for us yeah all right
thanks Phil thanks
Phil thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. club.com to join our
private community
[Music]